<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to a friende, touching Mardochai his age which helpeth much to holde the trueth, for that chiefe prophecie of our saluation in Gabriels seuenties: which shew, that most exactly 490, yeeres after the angels speach, Christ the most holy should be killed, to giue life. Dan 9.23.</title>
            <author>Broughton, Hugh, 1549-1612.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16990</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3870</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114813</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850036</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850036</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15219</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16990)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15219)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 656:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to a friende, touching Mardochai his age which helpeth much to holde the trueth, for that chiefe prophecie of our saluation in Gabriels seuenties: which shew, that most exactly 490, yeeres after the angels speach, Christ the most holy should be killed, to giue life. Dan 9.23.</title>
                  <author>Broughton, Hugh, 1549-1612.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By VVil. VVhite, in Cow-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Hugh Broughton.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Mardochai his age: a light to Gabriels seauenties.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mordecai --  (Biblical figure) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Esther --  Commentaries.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Chronology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15219:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15219:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Letter to a Friende, touching <hi>Mardochai</hi> his age;</p>
            <p>Which helpeth much to holde the trueth, for that chiefe Prophecie of our ſaluation in <hi>Gabriels</hi> Seuenties: which ſhew, that moſt exactly 490, yeares after the Angels ſpeach, Chriſt the moſt Holy ſhould be killed, to giue life. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.23.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>1.25.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The fooliſhneſſe of God is wiſer then men.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Wil. VVhite,</hi> in Cow-lane.
1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15219:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15219:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Printer to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT the Letter following might better be vnderſtood, I requeſted the Authour, that one ſpeciall Text might be ſet before it, as hee had tranſlated it. <hi>Daniel,</hi> 9.24. I heard him affirme, that none, for skill in Hebrew, would blame that Tranſlation: and though many differ, it was not for ignoraunce of the tongue; but by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite touching the matter, drawing the words as they iudged of the whole cauſe. Thus he tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that poynt, which was <hi>Gabriels</hi> ſpeach; who came to
<hi>Daniel,</hi> praying at the time of the Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning offering, or three of the clocke, or ninth houre by Scripture phraſe: (<note n="§" place="margin">For ſo he wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the letter.</note> at which houre 490. yeares after moſt exactly, our Lord gaue vp the Ghoſt, and told, that at the beginning of his<note n="*" place="margin">So the author taught. that euen the faythles Iew Aben Ezra vpon Dan. 9. begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the time from the word that came forth at Daniels pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and endeth it when Chriſt is ſealed. And that the Iew though he could not caſt the times particularly, nor knew Chriſt to be the moſt Holy, yet durſt not depart from the proprietie of plaine wordes, to peruert the ſpeach of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God; &amp; be wiſhed others that circumſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Such as begin &amp; end to that effect, may not make here a certaine num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, for an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine.</note> Prayer, came foorth the word (or anſwere from God) which he came to ſhew, and ſayth
<pb facs="tcp:15219:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>thus. <hi>Seauentie ſeauens (of yeares) are cut out, for thy people, and for thy holy Citie; to conſume wickedneſſe, and to aboliſh ſinnes, and to make reconciliation for iniquitie, and to bring righteouſneſſe euerlaſting, and to ſeale Viſion and Prophet, and to ſhew</hi> Chriſt, <hi>the</hi> Holy <hi>of</hi> Holy. <hi>Know and marke; from the out-going of the Word, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne and to build</hi> Ieruſalem,
<hi>vnto</hi> Chriſt <hi>the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſhalbe ſeauen ſeauens (of yeares,) and ſixtie and two ſeauens:</hi> (in th'other) <hi>it ſhall be reſtored and built, Street and Wall; and troublous shall theſe times be. In that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſixtie and two ſeauens,</hi> Chriſt <hi>shall be killed; and not for him ſelfe: thereupon the Citie and Holy place shall he deſtroy, the</hi> Gouernours <hi>owne people to come, &amp; their end shalbe with a Flood: and at the end of Warre, it shall haue a finall iudgement to deſolation. But hee shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the Testament for many the laſt Seauen; when in</hi> Halfe that Seauen, <hi>hee shall end the Sacrifice and Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Afterwardes, by an Armie abominable, hee shall make a deſolation, euen till vtter deſtruction, and finall iudgement flow vpon the deſolate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much for the Readers preparation, to vnderſtand the Epiſtle following.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:15219:3"/>
            <head>To his good friend A. T. of Mardochai his age: a light to
<hi>Gabriels</hi> Seauenties.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OV deſire to know of mee, in what age <hi>Mardochai</hi> lyued; becauſe you hold his times, to helpe much the truth of Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle, whereby ſundry Bookes of the holy Prophets may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be vnderſtood. Your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt is reaſonable; becauſe you rightly iudge of the profite aryſing by that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: For whereas the chiefe Prophecie in all the old Teſtament, touching the time of ſaluation, is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured, that of
<hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24. and alſo <hi>Dan.</hi> 11. <hi>Eſter, Ezra, Nehemiah, Aggi, Zachary,</hi> by reaſon that men attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute neare 100. yeares more then common likelihood can ſuffer, or ſome writers old and late, will graunt to theſe men after <hi>Babel</hi> was taken; I meane to <hi>Cyrus, Cambyſes, Darius Hiſtaſpis,</hi> and <hi>Xerxes.</hi> They who hold
<hi>Aſſuerus</hi> to be <hi>Xerxes,</hi> (who be the chiefeſt Patrons of that exceſſiue time) if it can be ſhewed that <hi>Mardochai</hi> was in Captiuitie 63. yeeres, muſt needes graunt that from <hi>Cyrus</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Some giue <hi>Cirus</hi> but three yeeres, &amp; that vnder
<hi>Cambyſes</hi> 7. to <hi>Darius Hyſtaſpis</hi> 12. y. as
<hi>Sedcrolam,</hi> and <hi>Xerxes</hi> bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 10. alnoe: ſome more, as in <hi>Clem. Alex. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> hath y. 30. <hi>Cambyſes</hi> 19. <hi>Darius Hyſtaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis</hi>
46. <hi>Xerxes</hi> 26. Their times before the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing of
<hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon,</hi> &amp; vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roigne, might well haue ſo much as other abridge from this: but from <hi>Babylons</hi> fal 30 yeere muſt be their moſt.</note> ſurpryſing of <hi>Babel,</hi> to <hi>Aſſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> end, when yet <hi>Mardochai</hi> was ſomewhat actiue: 30. yeeres agreeth more with the common courſe of life, then 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. And that being ſetled, touching yeares thence to
<hi>Tiberius</hi> 18. yeare: Some old Greeke ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt <pb facs="tcp:15219:4"/>will very well agree with vs for <hi>Daniels</hi> Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, to make vp 490. yeares. Wherefore your iudgement, carefull to know his times, muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed: and endeauour to ſatisfie your requeſt, muſt be vſed.</p>
            <p>The Scripture wherevpon diſputation of late gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, is this.
<hi>Eſter</hi> 2.5. <hi>In the Citie of</hi> Shuſhan, <hi>there was a certaine</hi> Iew <hi>whoſe name was</hi> Mordochai, <hi>the ſonne of</hi> Iair, <hi>the ſonne of</hi> Shimei, <hi>the ſonne of</hi> Kiſh, <hi>a man of</hi> Jemini,<note n="*" place="margin">The queſtion herevpon ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, whether <hi>Mardochai</hi> or <hi>Kish</hi> was of the Captiuity.</note>
               <hi>which had been caryed away from</hi> Ieruſalem <hi>with the Captiuitie that was caried away with</hi> Iechoniah <hi>king of</hi> Iudah,
<hi>whom</hi> Nebuchadnezar <hi>king of</hi> Babel <hi>had caried away; &amp; nouriſhed</hi> Hadaſſa, <hi>that is</hi> Eſter, <hi>his Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles daughter: for she had neither father nor mother; and the Maide was fayre &amp; beautifull to looke on: and after the death of her father &amp; her mother,</hi> Mardochai <hi>tooke her for his owne Daughter.</hi> To this text I thinke good to ioyne immediatly, another touching them, who were captiued with
<hi>Iechoniah,</hi> to ſhew that not only valient Men, but alſo Women and Babes, were then caryed captiue: of which Babes, <hi>Mardochai</hi> might be one. Thus it is written, 2. King. 24.14. <hi>And he caryed away all Ieruſalem, and all the Princes, and all the ſtrong men of Warre, euen ten thouſand into captiuitie, and all the Workemen &amp; cunning men: ſo none remayned, ſauing the poore people of the land.</hi> Now if none were left but the Poore of the earth, Noble-women &amp; Children muſt needes be in the reckoning of the Captiuitie. But let vs returne to the firſt text
<hi>Eſter</hi> 2.5. vpon which Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we muſt weigh what hath bin thought,<note place="margin">Of old time it hath bin hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and may be. I hold it doubtleſſe, that <hi>Mardochai</hi> by this text, was in the Captiuity. The ſame held alſo the moſt aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient; <pb facs="tcp:15219:4"/>that it may appeare, this opinion not to be new, but holden conſtantly of long time, the Father of TRVETH.</p>
            <p>The Greeke additions to <hi>Eſter,</hi> plainely ſhew, that in auncient time, <hi>Mardochai</hi> was holden to be of <hi>Iechonias</hi> captiuitie for thus it is written <hi>Eſter 11.2. Mardocheus the ſonne of Iairus, the ſonne of Semei, the ſonne of Kiſh, of the tribe of Beniamin, had a Dreame; a Iew dwelling in the citie of Suſis, a Neble man, that bare office in the kings Court, Hee was alſo one of the Captiuitie which Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chodonoſor the king of Babylon brought from Ieruſalem with Iechonias.</hi> That thoſe Greeke additions be very old, it appeareth by
<hi>Ioſ. Ben-gorion,</hi> whom <hi>Druſius</hi> thinketh to be <hi>Flanius Ioſephus:</hi> For <hi>Ben-gorion</hi> in his Hebrew ſtorie followeth them; and the Greeke Church ſtifly enough held them. Wherefore, if that age were now aliue, and called to an after reckoning for the <hi>Perſian</hi> continuance, I iudge by <hi>Mardochais</hi> age, they would willingly cutte off about a hundred yeares, for their ouerreaching Chronicle; and reioyce not a little, to haue <hi>Daniels</hi> times brought to plainnes. They did not onely of auncient dayes allow of the Greeke additions for <hi>Mardochais</hi> times;<note place="margin">The auncient Greekes by their owne graunt, would ſhorten much their accompt for the Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans yeares.</note> but in their owne writinges doe the like. <hi>Ioſephus</hi> ſayth, that
<hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dochai</hi> had been at <hi>Babylon. Clemens</hi> ſayth, that he was in the Captiuitie. So doth <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in <hi>Synopſi</hi> in
<hi>Heſter. Codrenus</hi> placeth <hi>Aſſuerus</hi> in the beginning of
<hi>Darius,</hi> and <hi>Cy.</hi> Monarchy. <hi>Zonarus</hi> much followeth
<hi>Ioſephus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pagnins</hi> care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tranſlation is voyde of doubt, that by it, <hi>Mardochai</hi> is of <hi>Iechonias</hi> captiuitie.</note> Theſe mens teſtimonies againſt their owne negligent accompt, ſhould ſeeme to be voyde of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialitie.</p>
            <p>The like I may ſpeake of the Latines. <hi>Pagnin</hi> his skil
<pb facs="tcp:15219:5"/>in Hebrew, giueth place to none Italian, former nor later. In his tranſlation of <hi>Eſter,</hi> out of doubt <hi>Mardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chai</hi> is a man of
<hi>Beniamin,</hi> which was caried captiue with <hi>Iechonias.</hi> The French glory of <hi>Vatablus,</hi> and his iudgement, by our learned Fathers, who put before the Bible his briefe ſumme touching it, hath been great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteemed.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vatablus</hi> agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth With <hi>Pag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nin,</hi> &amp; further ſpeaketh of <hi>Kiſh:</hi> Whom he holdeth him to be.</note>
               <hi>Vatablus</hi> remoueth the doubt further, ſheweth that
<hi>Kiſh</hi> there is named, to ſhew <hi>Mardochai</hi> to come of the Kinges ſeede. Now where ſome doubt why obſcure <hi>Kiſh</hi> father to
<hi>Saul,</hi> rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Saul,</hi> ſhould be recorded: for them a certaine <hi>Hebrew</hi> yeeldeth a reaſon that ſatisfieth me. As
<hi>Mardochai</hi> taught <hi>Eſter</hi> to hide her kindred: ſo the other
<hi>Iewes</hi> endeuored to doe,<note place="margin">Why <hi>Kish</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then <hi>Saul</hi> is named.</note> and kept the memorie of <hi>Mardochais</hi> nobilitie rather by <hi>Kiſh,</hi> famous amongſt them, and obſcure to ſtrangers, then by <hi>Saul,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Haman</hi> of <hi>Ameleck</hi> might haue heard of. If any deſpiſeth the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> reaſon, let him bring a better. With <hi>Pagnin</hi> and <hi>Vatablus</hi> agreeth
<hi>Arias Montanus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Arius Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, <hi>&amp;</hi> Treme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus <hi>tranſlatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi>
               </note> whoſe like if <hi>Spaine</hi> had bred many, the Pope ſhould haue been cloſely bitten to the heart. Though he follow the common Chronicle, yet he made conſcience of wreſting holy Scripture. <hi>Tremelius</hi> likwiſe, whoſe tranſlation giueth place to none (whom I could wiſh for many ſpeciall poynts, not to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by following the Heathen) he tranſlateth the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> ſo,<note place="margin">The common iudgement of Italy, France, Spaine, and Germany.</note> as ſpeaking, that <hi>Mardochai</hi> was of <hi>Iechonias</hi> captiuity. This <hi>Italy, Fraune, Spayne,</hi> &amp; <hi>Germany</hi> held.</p>
            <p>And leaſt any ſhould take aduantage by the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue
<hi>(Which,)</hi> to referre it to <hi>Kiſh,</hi> &amp; not to
<hi>Mardochai,</hi> they tranſlate the laſt antecedent before it;<note place="margin">Vir, <hi>not</hi> Viri.</note> that is, <hi>(MAN of Beniamin)</hi> in a caſe ioyned to <hi>Mardochai,</hi> and diſceauored from
<hi>Kiſh.</hi> Two reaſons mooued <pb facs="tcp:15219:5"/>them to that, (as I thinke): one, becauſe in the Hebrew vpon the word <hi>Kiſh,</hi> lyeth a ſtay of a King-accent, in force and forme like a Comma in Latin.<note place="margin">Tipheha the King-accent, vſually diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth.</note> An other was, becauſe a Sentence is ioyned on a Copulatiue; which cannot be remoued from <hi>Mardochai, who was caryed captiue, and nouriſhed Ester.</hi> Alſo it ſeemed to them ſenſeleſſ, to admit in the middeſt, a long Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration touching <hi>Kiſh,</hi> where the ſpeach began of
<hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dochai,</hi> and afterward to make a ſodaine ſteppe againe to
<hi>Mardochai:</hi> and ſo would I thinke. Theſe who commend vpon
<hi>Eſter,</hi> follow the ſame<note n="a." place="margin">
                  <hi>Lyra. Brenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Bullinger,</hi> and <hi>Lauaterus</hi> vpon
<hi>Eſter.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Lyra, Brentius, Bullinger, Lauaterus.</hi> The argument in the Bible tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated at <hi>Goneuah,</hi> before the Booke of
<hi>Eſter,</hi> draweth in the ſame yoke. And on the Latin <hi>Ioh. Benedictus.</hi> So the French doth, and many more. And whereas ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mardochai</hi> is <hi>named Ezra</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them who gaue their names to returne (if occaſion beſt ſerued ſo) in the 1. of <hi>Cyrus.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Mardochai</hi> is named amongſt them who did, or might returne from <hi>Babylon</hi> in the firſt of <hi>Cyrus.</hi> I ſee no reaſon why the many of them who affyrme euen that <hi>Mardochai</hi> there, to be <hi>Eſters</hi> coſen, ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected. I will not ſoone beleeue, that the prouidence of God would in Scripture ſo place names, that thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes of the painfulleſt and the wiſeſt, ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, as holding them the ſame men, when they are other. As <hi>Nehemias Ezra 2.2.</hi> is holden of the moſt, to be<note n="c." place="margin">R. <hi>Symeony</hi> there vpon <hi>Neh.</hi> 12.3. The authour of
<hi>Ezra</hi> 4. was watchful to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon opinion to make
<hi>Ezra</hi> to be of the captiuitie, as immediate ſonne to <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> killed at the third captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. 52 y. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the. 70. ended. Or <hi>Nehemias</hi> and
<hi>Ezra,</hi> ſeuerall treatiſes are purpoſed.</note> the ſame who is
<hi>Artaxaſt</hi> his Cup-bearer. And <hi>Ezra Nehe. 12.</hi> comming home in
<hi>Cyrus</hi> firſt, is hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> to be the ſame who wrote the Booke named ſo; and liued to the laſt times of the
<hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians;</hi> and by <hi>4 Ezra 3.</hi> may very well be. So no more will I admit two <hi>Mardochaies,</hi> then I will heere two <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> and two <hi>Ezras,</hi> ſeeing I ſee no reaſon why obſcure men ſhould be chiefe in catalogue of perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, <pb facs="tcp:15219:6"/>and famous men be left vnreckoned, who in open dealing haue the next glory to <hi>Zorobabel</hi> and
<hi>Ioſhua.</hi> But of the other two, <hi>Nehemias</hi> and <hi>Ezra,</hi> I may take ſome other time of a longer Diſcourſe. I will returne to
<hi>Mardochai.</hi> They who hold of the Pope, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their errour in giuing the <hi>Perſians</hi> too long a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance, yet would not in the perticular deale here agaynſt their conſcience: for their table in
<hi>Apparatu Bibliorum</hi> holdeth <hi>Mardochai Eſters</hi> kinſman, to be of the captiuitie of <hi>Iechonias,</hi> and alſo to be the ſame that is mentioned <hi>Ezra. 2.2.</hi> So <hi>Schubertus,</hi> and <hi>Lyra,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hold <hi>Mardochai</hi> much aboue. 100. yeere, then with
<hi>Burgenſis</hi> deny him to be of <hi>Iechonias</hi> captiuitie. And
<hi>Iohn Benedictus</hi> noteth (from <hi>Philo</hi>) that he lyued 198. yeeres. Likewiſe ſome of our owne countrey, who haue by authoritie written in notes ſimply enough, gathered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Codomanus,</hi> place
<hi>Mardochai</hi> ſo, that wel he might be of the captiuitie of
<hi>Iechoniah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Codomon</hi> &amp; his tranſlater ſimply ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene.</note> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that ſome who haue trauayled more in this kinde, would ſoone conclude that thereupon they muſt cut neare
100. yeeres from their owne accompt. The teſtimony of any againſt them ſelues, ſhould haue ſome force. <hi>Bucholcherus</hi> bringeth it as a moſt common opinion, that he liued in the dayes of <hi>Euil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merodach</hi> and
<hi>Balſaſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Hebrewes are not leaſt regarded for commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting as touching the Story, conteyned in proper ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Prophets. Of them I haue ſeene twelue ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Writers touching <hi>Eſter:</hi> By which all, it may be learned, that the Iewes helde <hi>Mardochai</hi> to be of
<hi>Iechonias</hi> Captiuitie; as the <hi>Talmud</hi> in <hi>Megillath Eſter,</hi> two <hi>Chaldy Paraphastes. Aben-Ezra, Solomoh-Iarchi:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:15219:6"/>which are ioyned in <hi>Bonbergius</hi> Bibles; ſeauen Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries printed in litle Bookes alone. <hi>Adde Midras Rabbah,</hi> who paſsing it ouer, as touchng plaine words, in the whole Diſcourſe ſheweth what the Authour thought. And ſeeing the Iewes euer ſince
<hi>Mardochais</hi> time, yearely in the moneth <hi>Adar,</hi> celebrate a Feaſt for the deliuerance by him. It would be too raſh to affirme ſo many thouſandes, now 2000. yeares, not to vnderſtand his ſtory: but in a<note n="*" place="margin">Whether <hi>Kiſh</hi> or <hi>Mardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chai</hi> ſhould be of the captiuitie.</note> tricke of Grammer, all to be ouerreached. Moreouer, cloſely they giue a bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter frumpe to ſome Chriſtians in <hi>Sepher Iuchaſim</hi> in the word <hi>Ezra,</hi> when they ſayne <hi>Mardochoi</hi> to liue 400. yeares teaching their children thereby, how vnskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full many of our ſide are in the ſtory of Scripture:<note place="margin">The Iewes floute Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ignorant of <hi>Mardochaies</hi> times.</note> for if this be true, that no Male were caryed with <hi>Iecho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> but fitte then for warre, and vnder the tearmes of, <hi>All Ieruſalem, 2. Kin, 24.</hi> Women and Babes be not conteyned: If alſo from <hi>Zedekias</hi> captiuitie the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentie yeares muſt begin, and <hi>Mardochai</hi> liue in the end of the
<hi>Perſians:</hi> and if <hi>Euſebius</hi> times, and <hi>Ieromes</hi> holde: then by our aſſertions muſt <hi>Mardochai</hi> be hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en towardes
400. yeere olde. But iuſtly is <hi>Euſebius</hi> blamed of <hi>Iohannes Benidictus,</hi> and <hi>Marianus Soctus.</hi> And <hi>Ierome</hi> may not be cited for them that would haue <hi>Mardochai</hi> borne in the fourth age after the captiuitie. For <hi>Scaliger,</hi> and ſuch as leane vpon him, hold that
<hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> (who buylt the Temple<note n="*" place="margin">So <hi>S. Jerome</hi> thinketh, as do ſom Hebrewes and <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yn.</hi> vpon <hi>Ag.</hi>
               </note> 17. yere after
<hi>Cyrus</hi> firſt) was after <hi>Mardochai:</hi> So that he will of force haue <hi>Mardochai</hi> neare <hi>Cyrus</hi> times. And <hi>Euſebius</hi> may be confuted by himſelfe, citing <hi>Hellanicus</hi> out of <hi>Celemens,</hi> who writeth thus: <hi>Atoſſa</hi> the Queene of the <hi>Perſians</hi> firſt inuented Epiſtles.<note place="margin">Hillanie us <hi>of</hi> Atoſsa.</note> Though Epiſtles were vſed of <pb facs="tcp:15219:7"/>olde, as in
<hi>Iuda</hi> and <hi>Iſrael:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jl. zeta in Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lero phontes.</note> alſo in <hi>Homer II.</hi> yet when Heathen ſkant vſed written recordes, the letters ſent by <hi>Heſter Adoſſa</hi> to 127. Prouinces, might well be the moſt ancient for famous &amp; freſh memory in
<hi>Helianicus</hi> dayes, whom <hi>Thucidides</hi> nameth as his former. And herein the antiquitie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thucidides</hi> dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the times of <hi>Peloponne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas</hi> warres.</note> who had followed the games of
<hi>Olympia,</hi> to teach of mans redeemer againſt expreſſe word in
<hi>Daniels</hi> ninth, controll themſelues, and call times to as ſhort a reckoning, as trueth hereafter much by Heathen accompt wil require. An
<hi>Hebrew</hi> diſputeth learnedly,<note place="margin">An Hebrewes reaſon of <hi>Eſters</hi> tymes.</note> to teach vs that <hi>Eſters</hi> ſtories fell out ſoone after the captiuitie: becauſe many of rare godlyneſſe muſt needes then be amongſt them, that God ſhould in ſundry places, giue them ſo great glory. It is not commonly ſeene, that the age vnafflicted, ſhould be of more godlyneſſe, then they who before, had felt Gods hand. <hi>Ioſhuahs</hi> elders and their poſteritie teach vs ſo to thinke: likewiſe <hi>Dauids</hi> age, &amp; <hi>Robeames.</hi> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, the Apoſtle giueth that company a ſinguler teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, <hi>Hebr. 11.24.</hi> who by fayth auoyded the edge of the ſword. I doubt not, but that of them it is ſpoken there. Ouer &amp; beſides, the prophecie of <hi>Ieremy</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the good Figges, may very well haue accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in
<hi>Mardochai.</hi> And <hi>Lyra</hi> would thinke, that in
<hi>Mardochaies</hi> ſtory, mention is made of <hi>Iechonias</hi> captiuitie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lyra</hi> vpon <hi>Ier.</hi> 24.</note> to ſhew, namely in ſome, that fauour of God performed, which in the good Figges was ſhewed. Heere I may for the helpe of the Reader, abridge
<hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> wordes, from <hi>Ier. 24.</hi> To him God ſhewed <hi>Two basket of Figges: one of good Figges, the other of naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Figges. After</hi> Iechonias, <hi>the Nobles and Artificers of</hi> Iudah <hi>were caried daptiues: As the good Figges, would <pb facs="tcp:15219:7"/>God know thoſe captiues, and bring them home: and as the naughty Figges, would God giue</hi> Zedekias
<hi>and his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for a terrible plague.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, this I thinke, and hold, that none euer denied
<hi>Mardochai</hi> to be of <hi>Iechonias</hi> captiuitie, but ſuch as<note n="*" place="margin">Eyther of themſelues, or led by others.</note> follow the reckoning of <hi>Olympia</hi> Games. All this conſidered, I iudge it will not ſoone take place, that ſome would teach this opinion to be new, or vntrue, that <hi>Mardochai</hi> is ſayd to be of the Captiuitie of
<hi>Iecho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias.</hi> And this of <hi>Mardochai</hi> being graunted, my ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt combaters (I truſt) will not deny, but that <hi>Daniel</hi> might well vnderſtand his owne wordes: and the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenties, from the houre of their vtteraunce, and firſt yeare of <hi>Darius</hi> and <hi>Cyrus,</hi> in propriety of ſpeach, draw vs vnto the yeare wherein our Lord by death, brought light and life to the world. Thus I thought good, though as faſt as my Pen could run, to write my minde touching <hi>Mardochai:</hi> that you might be better confirmed to hold the trueth of <hi>Daniels</hi> ſeauens: the plainnes &amp; propriety whereof, many Chriſtians ſtriue more to make vncertaine, then did the <hi>Iewes;</hi> whom your ſelfe heard at
<hi>Franckfurt</hi> and <hi>Wormes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I will ioyne a particuler reckonig, agreeable to
<hi>Daniels</hi> Seauens: euen from ſuch as for the whole, agree not wholly with that, which I ſteadfaſtly hold to be the trueth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cyrus</hi> 3. yeare: <hi>Schubert.</hi> Well may he haue reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned 27. yeare before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cambyſes Artaxaſt.</hi> 7. yeares: <hi>Herodot.</hi> But be reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his fathers life 2. yeares of them, at the leaſt: as appeareth by conferring <hi>Ezra 4.</hi> with <hi>Dan. 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15219:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſſuerus</hi> holden moſt commonly to be <hi>Darius Hystaſpis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">By arguments drawen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> al through compared with Heathen, it may well be prooued that
<hi>Aſſuerus</hi> is <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Hiſtaſpis,</hi> &amp; by
<hi>Heſter</hi> 3.7. compared with cha. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. we may wel thinke that he reigned nothing neare
36. yeers <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch,</hi> as ſome Heathen think.</note> 12. yeeres in
<hi>Seder Olam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Xerxes,</hi> of whoſe ſole gouernment <hi>Ezra</hi> maketh no mention: onely <hi>Dan. 11.</hi> He is ſayd to be the rich King, that ſhould ſtyrre all againſt <hi>Grecia.</hi> Some hold him to be
<hi>Aſſuerus</hi> in <hi>Heſter.</hi> Vpon their aſſertion I deſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>Mardochai: Schubertus</hi> graunteth him 10. yeeres of ſole gouernement: but <hi>Tremelius</hi> ioyneth them to his fathers raigue, and maketh him but viceroy: and all 20.</p>
            <p>And theſe be the chiefe Kings whoſe accompt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth Commenters vpon <hi>Daniel, Heſter, Ezra, Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mias, Aggai,</hi> and
<hi>Zachary,</hi> againſt the playne ſimplicitie: which thoſe bookes proceſſe do require. Of them I purpoſe to write other ſeuerall Mreatiſes, to confirme this accompt in effect<note place="margin">The ſhortnes of the tyme from <hi>Cyrus.</hi> to <hi>Neh.</hi> gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſeene by the age of theſe men, <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raia, Ieremy, Eſdras, Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, Hattus, Shecaniah, Malluc, Rehum, Meremoth Abiah, Mia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, Bilga, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ai:</hi> which came with
<hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robabel, Neh.</hi> 12. and after the Anylding of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> helped <hi>Nehemiah Neh.</hi>
               </note> which others <hi>Iewes</hi> and
<hi>Gentiles</hi> holde, and to ouerthrow that exceſſiue reckoning, which the Games of <hi>Olympia</hi> cauſe to more harme for <hi>Iewes,</hi> then the Idole <hi>Iouis Olimpij</hi> was lothſome in their Temple in olde time. Now marke other Kinges hence from <hi>Clemens 1. Strom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Artaxerxes 41.</hi> His 20. yeere finiſheth ſeauen ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens to the buylding of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and full finiſhyng of the Temple, as writeth <hi>Aben Ezra, Tremelius, Bero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aldus, Wolphius:</hi> &amp; the French notes before <hi>Ezra</hi> touch it. The Greekes <hi>Ioſephus, Clemens, Euſebius, Cedrenus,</hi> ending the Temple in that time, had relation to the ſeauen ſeauens <hi>Dan. 9.</hi> though the
<hi>Olympiades</hi> carry them ſomewhat aſide; but by a friendly cenſure, one might cite them to that textes meaning, wherevpon they ſtayed; ſpecially ſeeing otherwiſe they are litle <pb facs="tcp:15219:8"/>conſtant, or worthy credite, but when many confirme the matter with them.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>allis
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſter, ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g to <hi>Alexanders</hi> dayes ſheweth that it was but a ſhort time afterward betwixt both.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Darius</hi> 8. yeares.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> 42. yeares. In this Kinges dayes,
<hi>Xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophon</hi> and <hi>Cteſias</hi> liued, and wrote of him,
<hi>Plutarch</hi> wrote alſo, and many Grecians more. The more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent be the wicked <hi>Iewes,</hi> which leaue him out, to ſhorten the time, and diſanull by all other extreamitie, <hi>Daniels</hi> Seauens.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ochus</hi> 3. yeares.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Darius</hi> 6. yeares.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Their yeares in all, are 130.</p>
            <list>
               <head>The Greekes.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> 6. Herein I ſomewhat mende
<hi>Clemens</hi> from all other <hi>Grecians.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ptolomy Lagi</hi> 40. yeares.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pto. Philadelphus 27.</hi> y. rather.
<hi>37.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pto. Euergetus</hi> 25. yeares.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pto. Philopater</hi> 17. yeares.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pto. Epiphanes</hi> 24. yeares.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pto. Philometor</hi> 35. yeares.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Clemens</hi> coppy omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth tenne yeares, in ſome one; by like in <hi>Philad.</hi> to finiſh the ſumme of 294. years: which ſum, in two places he hath.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pto. Phiſcon</hi> 29. yeares.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pto. Lathurus</hi> 36. yeares. <hi>Strabo</hi> would place <hi>Lathurus</hi> before <hi>Phyſcon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pto. Dionyſius</hi> 29. yeares.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cleopatra</hi> 22. yeares.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The whole ſumme is 300, yeares.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15219:9"/>
            <p>From <hi>Cleopatras</hi> ouerthrow by <hi>Augustus,</hi> to 18. of
<hi>Tiberius</hi> 60. yeares,<note place="margin">Form <hi>Auguſtus</hi> 15. who is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>g<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned 56. to 18. further. 60. y.</note> by accompts of the old and the later.</p>
            <p>And this I haue layde downe, that you might better know, where the
<hi>Iewes</hi> helpe the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to hold the trueth, for what times the Scriptures fully helpe vs and where the <hi>Iewes</hi> may eaſily be confuted, and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> agree commonly. This being well weighed, you may ſee that in <hi>Mardochai,</hi> Antiquirie and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueltie muſt both agree, to caſt <hi>Daniels</hi> Seauens: as I ſhewed in the <hi>Conſent of Scripture,</hi> which I wrote.</p>
            <p>This one Treatiſe of <hi>Mardochas</hi> well conſidered, will make men more capable of trueth, in ſundry argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for manifeſting of
<hi>Daniel.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>HVGH BROVGHTON.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15219:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
